Princetoniana Committee Oral History Project Records, 1994-2015: Preliminary Finding Aid AC259
University Archives
- Series 2: Princetoniana Committee Oral History Interviews, 1977-2015 May 12; 3 boxes
  - Brendan Byrne '49, 2010 January; 1 box (Box 2)
    In the interview, Byrne describes serving in the Air Force; flying B-17s out of Italy; being admitted to Princeton through an entrance examination after the war; being admitted to Harvard Law School before completing his undergraduate degree; leaving Law School to finish his undergraduate education; his thesis on proportional representation in municipal government; running for Princeton's track team; living in Little Hall; and being a member of Cottage Club. He mentions John McGeehan, Boy Meyner, classmate Dick Martell, Professors "Buzzer" Hall and Wilbur Samuel Howell, Newark lawyer Joseph Weintraub, and Mayor of Jersey City Paul Jordan.
  - Renato (Ronnie) R. Carazzai, 2011 July 21; 1 box (Box 2)
    Renato "Ronnie" R. Carazzai worked for Princeton as an electrician starting in 1952.
    Carazzai attended Princeton High School. He describes many aspects of his Princeton employment experience including the growth of the electric department; the student body dress code; Public Safety; students building a prank grave for an unpopular professor; the "student take over" of New South in the late 1960s; taking the 1935 clapper from Nassau; the neglect of Reunion Hall; remodeling Witherspoon; Joe DiMaggio filming a Mr. Coffee commercial in Dickinson; Muhammad Ali's speech at Alexander Hall; the discovery of 7 rifles in a Campbell Hall room; a co-worker stealing a student's jacket; the Nude Olympics; cleaning up after and interacting with students; students camping in front of Nassau; students trying to set Nassau on fire in 1958; alcoholism among maintenance staff; gas explosion in Aaron Burr; construction of Wu Hall; Rutgers covering Princeton cannon with dirt; pigeon eradication on campus; Jadwin Hall accelerator; dumbwaiter in Nassau to prevent people from walking on stairs; construction of Jadwin Cage; maintenance during reunions; and the 9/11 memorial between East Pyne and Nassau. He mentions administrator Jim Henry, student Brooke Shields, faculty member Freddie Fox, student Jack McCarthy, maintenance director and alum Charlie Crank, President Goheen, and supervisor Eddie Pondet.
  - Paula Chow, 2015 May 12; 1 box (Box 4)
    Paula Chow is the founder and former director of the Princeton University International Center.
    Chow discusses her life as an international undergraduate in the United States; her early years as a member of the University League; weekly University League discussions for foreign wives of faculty members; Louise Sayen's English program for foreign students; the creation of the International Center; co-directing the International Center with Sayen after being sanctioned by Provost Albert Rees; the first annual International Festival; moving the Center to Murray Dodge Hall with the blessing of Dean of the Chapel Ernest Gordon; becoming a part of the university administration; donation of $5 million from Kathryn Davis and Shelby Cullom Davis to the International Center; student projects through the center; the relationship between Chinese and Chinese-American students on campus; an article in Princeton Magazine from 2010 about the control of the Davis International Center shifting to the vice-provost for international activities; her final visit to the Davis International Center after her retirement; and her honorary induction into the class of 2010. She mentions president of the University League Mary Ellen Bowen, James Sayen '38, Dean of Undergraduate Students Kathleen Deignan, foreign student advisor Janina Issawi, history professor Jeremy Adelman, Diana Davies, Vice Provost of Campus Life Janet Dickerson, Director of the Davis International Center Jaqueline Leighton, and Gordon Wu.
  - Stuart Duncan '50, 2013 September 23; 1 box (Box 4)
    Stuart Duncan, Class of 1950, majored in English and minored in American Civilization.
    In the transcript, Duncan talks about attending Brooks and Wooster prep schools, coming to college at 16 with a government scholarship, but leaving immediately to fight in the war. He discusses accelerated classes; compulsory chapel attendance excluding veterans; failing Spanish; the differences between veteran and non-veteran students; his membership in Tower Club; loose alcohol restrictions for veterans; teaching at a prep school in Connecticut after graduating; his family's firm Leah and Perrins Worcestershire Sauce; producing theater in New York; writing for New Brunswick and Princeton newspapers; the P-Rade; the Arch of 79 P-Rade cheer; serving as grand marshal of the P-Rade; resistance towards coeducation; having live tigers in the P-Rades; the tiger escape incident near 1979 Arch; and Da Vinci hats at Reunions. He mentions alum Frank Gorman.
  - Ronnie Gail Emden '74, 2008 July 20; 1 box (Box 2)
    Ronnie Gail Emden, Class of 1974, majored in Biology, and participated in the Program of Science and Human Affairs.
    In her interview, Emden talks about growing up in New York; attending public high school; Princeton's coeducation announcement; living in a coed Witherspoon dorm; the quick adjustment to women on campus; being part of The Prince staff; Larry DuPraz's resistance to women on The Prince; having no physical education requirement for women; the term "girl" versus "coed"; meeting her husband, '72, at Princeton; socioeconomic issues being greater than gender differences; women and eating clubs; membership in Tower Club; the bicker for men versus women; women trying to steal the clapper; the women's "Save 'Spoon" campaign; the dress code; football games; and the Princeton alumni experience. She mentions Dean of Women Halcy Bohen, faculty Anne Wood and Nancy Weiss, and classmate Karen Haddy.
  - Harold Erdman '46, 2011 September 21; 1 box (Box 2)
    Harold Erdman, Class of 1946, majored in Engineering and served as chairman of the 40th Reunion in 1986.
    Erdman mentions his grandfather, who was class of 1886 and a teacher at Princeton Seminary and his father, Charles R. Erdman Jr., who was class of 1919, mayor of Princeton Bureau from 1938 to 1949, and taught politics at Princeton. He talks about attending Lawrenceville; the admissions' bias towards Lawrenceville; the freshman black hat dress code; Cane Spree; playing varsity hockey; signing up for the Navy in 1943 and being sent to Yale with the V-12 Program; Army personnel in classes; the social and intellectual environment of Princeton compared to Yale; working for Reynolds Metal Company; Roosevelt's Presidency; and Pearl Harbor. He also mentions hockey Coach Dick Vaughan and Engineering School Dean Condit.
  - Richard Eu '44, 2014 October 28; 1 box (Box 4)
    Richard Eu, Class of 1944, majored in English.
    Eu talks about coming to America for the first time for college from Singapore; the effect of the war on campus; receiving draft exemption because of his immigrant status; getting thesis submission extension because of a lack of research resources during the war; being one of two Asians at Princeton; membership in Key and Seal Club; setting up Princeton in Asia in Singapore; starting the Princeton Alumni Association in Singapore; competing on the fencing team; being featured in Time Magazine for his friendship with Japanese classmate, Ken "Ike" (Kentaro Ikeda '44); Cane Spree; girls coming to Princeton on the weekends; the lack of diversity; and coeducation. He mentions Professors Frank Graham and Finch, and friend George Shelling '43.
  - Sally Ann Fields '73, 2014 June 21; 1 box (Box 4)
    Sally Ann Fields graduated in 1973 with a degree in Statistics. She served on the Executive Committee Council of the Princeton University Community and was the first woman to get her name put on the wall at Jadwin Gym.
    Fields talks about growing up in Wilmington; playing varsity tennis and squash; the reaction of male classmates to females; living in Pyne Hall; the lack of female sports facilities; the way the professors treated women; the perception of female staff by the student body and male staff; other women coming to Princeton on weekends; and being a member of Tower Club. She mentions the Director of Women's Athletics Marilee Dean, Sociology Professor Suzanne Keller, Dean Halcy Bowen, and classmate Wendy Zaharko.
  - Macon Paine Finley '77, 2010 February 19; 1 box (Box 2)
    Macon Paine Finley, Class of 1977.
    Finley attended John Burroughs School before coming to Princeton, following her sister, who was class of 1975. She was a Residential College Advisor, and played varsity basketball, but quit. She dated and married her classmate, Peter Finley, who was the president of Ivy Club. She discusses feeling included and being treated fairly in the newly coed environment; the treatment of women and men by professors; living in Wilson College; watching Valerie Bell become the first African-American female student body president; the African-American representation in the student body; singing in the Glee Club; and the tensions with eating clubs becoming non-bicker and allowing women to join.
  - John Fleming *63, 2009 May 13; 1 box (Box 2)
    John Fleming graduated from Oxford University in 1958 and was a Rhodes Scholar. He completed his Ph.D. at Princeton University in 1963. He served as Director of Graduate Studies at Princeton University and as a University of South Sewannee, University of Wisconsin, and Princeton professor.
    Fleming discusses finishing his Ph.D. work in one year; living in the Graduate College; Vietnam War protests; the leftist presence at Princeton; the Institute for Defense Analyses presence and protests against it; coeducation; dishonesty in campus publications; the honor code; technological advances at Princeton; and working for D.W. Robertson, his supervisor at Princeton.
  - Peter H.B. Frelinghuysen '38, 2010 January; 1 box (Box 2)
    Peter H.B. Frelinghuysen, Class of 1938, majored in History. He attended Yale Law School and served 11 terms in the U.S. House of Representatives for New Jersey. He also served on the Council of the Princeton University Community.
    In his interview, Frelinghuysen mentions attending Princeton and rooming with his twin brother, his father, class of 1924, and his son, class of 1963. He describes the 1924 kilts; living in Henry and Tyler Dormitories; taking Spanish and Greek; the effect of the Great Depression; practicing law at Simpson Thatcher; serving in the Navy; running for public office in 1952; and his twin brother working for the State Department. He also mentions classmates Alistair Martin and Gerry Ford, and President Goheen.
  - Moore (Mosie) Gates, Jr. '48, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 2)
    Moore "Mosie" Gates, Jr. graduated, Class of 1948, majored in History. His father was class of 1916.
    Gates mentions that his uncle was Assistant Dean of the College and an Assistant Professor and that admissions policies were loose. He describes various aspects of his experience at and after Princeton, including the high Army to civilian makeup of the student body; joining the Navy while at Princeton; the first black students; carrying dummy rifles on campus; living in Pyne Hall; playing varsity soccer; the married members of the student body; being a member of Cottage Club; the wartime sentiment on campus; casualties within the student body; writing his thesis on Woodrow Wilson and the League of Nations; and interacting with Dean of Admissions Rad Heermance and Professor "Buzzer" Hall.
  - Charles Gillispie, 2011 April 14; 1 box (Box 2)
    Charles Gillipsie graduated from Wesleyan University in 1940 and majored in Chemistry. He is Princeton's Dayton Stockton Professor of History of Science, Emeritus. He completed his graduate studies at Harvard and MIT. He wrote Genesis and Geology and The Edge of Objectivity, and edited the Dictionary of Scientific Biography.
    In his interview, Gillipsie discusses entering the Army's chemical corps; being a platoon leader and company commander in the European theatre for a heavy mortar unit; teaching at Princeton; precepting a class for Robert Palmer on the French Revolution; the meaning and evolution of the history of science subject; academic departments' location changes; the growth of the University; the creation of the Sachs Scholarship; and the precept system. He mentions Chairman of History Joe Strayer, freshman advisee Dan Sachs, and President Dodds.
  - James Henderson '56, 2007 November 9; 1 box (Box 2)
    James Henderson, Class of 1956, majored in the Woodrow Wilson School. He taught at the Naval Academy about geopolitics and communism. He also attended Harvard Business School.
    Henderson talks about growing up in Culver and his father working for Culver Military Academy; his thesis on employees' attitudes in the workplace; Princeton Junction and Back train; Princeton students from East Coast prep schools; the Orange Key Society; Navy ROTC; his membership in Quadrangle Club; serving in the Navy for five years; being a research assistant to Harvard Professor General Georges Doriot; working at American Research and Development; being COO, President, and CEO of Cummins; and serving on the Princeton Board as Charter Trustee. He mentions Professor Ebenstein, faculty Eric Rogers and Alpheus T. Mason, Dean Lippincott, Alumni Relations Head Don Griffin, classmates Bob McCartney and Neil Rudenstine, and Trustee Chair Manning Brown.
  - James Hester '46, 2011 November 16; 1 box (Box 2)
    James Hester, Class of 1946, majored in Humanities and History. He won the Rhodes Scholarship in 1947 and served in the Korean War for the Marine Corps. He served as Executive Dean of Arts and Sciences, Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, and President at New York University.
    Hester mentions his father, who was a chaplain in the Navy. He discusses growing up in Long Beach; accelerated classes; sophomores hazing freshmen by taking their clothes; Flag Day hazing; his membership in Cap and Gown Club; the fire at Dillon Gym; being sent to Parris Island and Quantico in 1945 with the Marine V-12 Program; attending Japanese Language School with the Marines; studying at Oxford; and working with Dr. Gallup in advertising research. He mentions Presidents Dodds and Goheen.
  - A.C. (Reeves) Hicks '46, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 2)
    A.C. Hicks, Class of 1946. His father was class of 1922. He was president of his alumni class.
    Hicks talks about growing up in Princeton; attending Exeter; girls coming to Princeton on the weekends; accelerated classes; the effect of the war on campus; participating in the Marine V-12 Program; playing varisty football; the serious academic atmosphere on campus; the effects of the Great Depression; and the war's negative effect on administration and staff. He mentions Dr. Albert Einstein and Professor Robert George.
  - Jon Hlafter '61 *63, 2013 May 24; 1 box (Box 4)
    Jon Hlafter, Class of 1961, majored in Architecture. He graduated with an M.F.A. in Architecture in 1963, and is the University Architect, Emeritus. He served as Princeton's Assistant to the Director of Physical Planning, and eventually, Acting Director. He also served as a Fellow in the American Institute of Architects and as a member of the Committee on Undergraduate Residential Life.
    In his interview, Hlafter describes Princeton's Architecture Department; the role of the Advisory Committee in campus architecture; the conversion of President Inn to Forbes; the creation of the Third World Center for women; the formation of the residential college system; building Spelman, Palmer Stadium, and Whitman; the evolution of Princeton's architecture; and preserving campus buildings. He mentions Director of Physical Planning and Alum Jack Moran, Grounds and Buildings Committee Trustee and Alum Stephen Voorhess, Professors Labatut and Michael Graves, President Goheen, Vice Provost Dick Spies, Architect Rodolfo Macahdo, and Architect and Alum Elizabeth Plater-Zyberk.
  - Herb Hobler '44, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 2)
    Herb Hobler, Class of 1944, majored in Spanish and minored in Music. His brother Ed was class of 1939, and his brother Wells was class of 1941.
    Hobler discusses the Westminster Society; composing music for Triangle; playing varsity basketball and junior varsity football and running track; describes discrimination of three black students on the basketball team; bicker; his membership in Tiger Inn; the campus wartime atmosphere; not participating in accelerated classes; his father's position of founder Chairman of Benton and Bowles; and being part of the March 19, 1945 Tokyo fire raid. He mentions Music Professor Roy Dickinson Welch, classmate Ed Cone, Professor Castro, President Dodds, and Coach Cappy Cappon.
  - Robert Hollander '55, 2012 June 5; 1 box (Box 2)
    Robert Hollander, Class of 1955, majored in French-English and was a Professor in European Literature in the Department of French and Italian, Emeritus. He was also a founding member of the Comparative Literature department and worked on the Princeton and Dartmouth Dante digitization and translation projects. He has published about 60 poems, 140 articles, and 29 books.
    In the interview, Hollander talks about growing up in New York City during the Depression; his father's ('16) experience facing Jewish discrimination; financial aid; the all-male atmosphere; starting to drink heavily during his last three years; his membership in Cannon Club; teaching at and being fired from Columbia; becoming master of Butler College; improving food quality at Princeton; the Dartmouth and Princeton Dante digitization and translation projects; becoming an assistant professor in 1962 and tenured professor in 1967 at Princeton; focusing on Dante; and starting Dante reunions. He mentions Jewish football player Frank Glick '16, thesis advisor Ed Sullivan, Professor Ira O. Wade, and his successor Simone Marchesi.
  - Stan Katz, 2013 January 14; 1 box (Box 4)
    Stan Katz majored in History and Literature at Harvard. He received his Ph.D. from Harvard in history, and began teaching there. In 1963 he was made Senior Tutor of Harvard's Leverett House. He was an Assistant Professor at the University of Wisconsin. He went to Harvard Law School and taught law at the University of Chicago, where he became the Associate Dean. He came to Princeton to teach in 1978 and taught law part time at the University of Pennsylvania. He is a Senior Fellow of the Woodrow Wilson School.
    Katz discusses growing up in Chicago; attending Harvard, believing it to be more accepting of Jewish students; serving as the President of the American Council of Learned Societies; teaching at Princeton on public policy, philanthropy, and civil society; precepts; the Woodrow Wilson School becoming non-selective; the lack of faculty governance at Princeton; the Jewish community; and the lack of athletes in the selective Woodrow Wilson School program. He is on the board of the Foundation for the Princeton Public Library, and has remained active with Princeton's Pace Center, the Office of Religious Life, and the Princeton Alumni corps. He mentions Princeton Professor Doug Greenberg, the first Master of Forbes John Wilson, and Presidents Bowen and Tilghman.
  - Thomas Kean '57, 2009 April 20; 1 box (Box 3)
    Thomas H. Kean, Class of 1957. He received his Ph.D. from Columbia in History. He began his political career in 1967, and became the governor of New Jersey in 1981, and subsequently a Trustee of Princeton.
    Kean discusses his family lineage tracing back to the Continental Congress; his father's career in Congress; growing up in Washington D.C.; attending St. Mark's; writing his thesis on his family's history, using family letters; the lack of an African-American presence on campus; Whig-Clio Society debates on campus diversity; completing the Army's 6-month program; working on Wall Street; focusing on marginalized populations in his governor campaign; and winning 60% of the black vote in his election. He mentions Professor R.R. Palmer, Wesley Craven, and Eric Goldman.
  - Edmund (Mike) Keeley '48, 2011 August 9; 1 box (Box 3)
    Edmund "Mike" Keeley, Class of 1948, majored in English. He attended Wadham College at Oxford and returned to Princeton to teach English and Creative Writing. He served on the Princeton faculty for 40 years.
    Keeley speaks about growing up abroad and being prevented from returning to Greece by the State Department in 1939; committing minor juvenile delinquencies; attending Princeton without prerequisite college board exams; incidents of Jewish discrimination in admissions; joining the Navy after freshman year; delayed graduation; the all-male environment; the required freshman Shakespeare course; volunteering for and teaching at the American Farm School; being the Vice President of Campus Club; working to dismantle bicker; winning the Grind Cup for highest GPA in Campus Club but hiding it out of embarrassment; serving as a faculty fellow in Stevenson Hall; helping to found the Republican Club and later regretting its creation; organizing Chapman Revercomb, Richard Nixon, and Hartley to speak to the Republican Club; the GI Bill; and serving on the disciplinary committee. He mentions Dean of Admissions Heermance, classmates Roger Saleeby, W.S. Merwin, and Galway Kinnell, Professor Willard Thorp, and President Dodds.
  - Dorothy Kemper '72, 2007 November 9; 1 box (Box 3)
    Dorothy Kember, Class of 1972, majored in English and came to Princeton in 1970 after completing her first two years at Wellesley.
    Kember discusses transferring to Princeton; growing up as an "army brat"; living in Princeton Inn Dormitory; the relatively welcoming environment for females; joining Triangle as a departmental requirement; touring with Triangle and performing Cracked Ice; Triangle being non-audition. She mentions Wellesley classmate Hillary Clinton, Princeton classmate Mimi Danly, Dean Helsey, and Preceptor Carlos Baker.
  - Shepard Kimberly '45, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 3)
    Shepard Kimberly, Class of 1945, majored in Philosophy and graduated with honors.
    In the interview, Kimberly talks about his accelerated graduation date due to the war; growing up in Buffalo; attending Hill School on scholarship and coming to Princeton with several classmates; his Hill School classmates at Princeton flunking out due to alcoholism; Pearl Harbor; the draft; being sent to Fort Niagara during sophomore year; dealing with Japanese prisoners during war; his membership in Key and Seal Club; having a child during his junior year; living in the Butler apartments; and classmates with wives and children. He mentions his godfather, '15, Dean of Admissions Heermance, and President Dodds.
  - Harold Kuhn *1950, Part I, 2011 June 8; 1 box (Box 3)
    Harold Kuhn graduated from Princeton's Graduate School in 1950. He is a recipient of the JSK Fellowship and won a best paper prize from the Office of Naval Research, subsequently named the Kuhn Prize. He received national acclaim in Hungary for his research. He also served as Chairman of Graduate Studies in Economics.